Guide to the Graduate and Professional Student Council records, 1968-2017 UA.31.10.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Graduate and Professional Student Council records
1968-2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Graduate and Professional Student Council
UA.31.10.0001
2.5 Linear Feet
0.52 Gigabytes
The Graduate and Professional Student Council aims to represent the social and academic interests of graduate students to the Duke University community. The Council was previously known as the Graduate Student Association. Records contain correspondence, minutes, constitutions, notes, membership lists, questionnaires, financial records, newsletters, and guidebooks. Major subjects include Graduate and Professional Student Council, Duke University student life, the Graduate School at Duke University, student organizations, Terry Sanford, student participation in administration, student housing, and tuition costs. Materials range in date from 1968 to 2017 (bulk 1968-1976 and 2013-2017).
2500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Graduate and Professional Student Council records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973-2019.
Historical Note
The Graduate and Professional Student Council (GPSC) represent all of the graduate and professional students at Duke. It was formed in 1981, "resurrected," in the words of one member "from the ashes of the Graduate Student Association" (1968-1978). The GPSC spent many of its formative years fighting for the recognition of the organization itself and for graduate students. Several issues addressed by the GPSC included entrance into athletic events by graduate students, increased representation on University committees; voting privileges and representation on Board of Trustees committees, and a student activity fee to provide funds for the GPSC.
For a more detailed history and overview of the GPSC's activities in the 1980s consult "An Orientation to the Graduate and Professional Student Council" by Barrett E. Koster housed in box 1 of this collection.
Collection Overview
Records contain correspondence, agendas and minutes, constitutions, resolutions, notes, membership lists, questionnaires, financial records, newsletters, guidebooks, and photographs from both the Graduate Student Association and the Graduate and Professional Student Council. Major subjects include Graduate and Professional Student Council, Duke University student life, the Graduate School at Duke University, student organizations, Terry Sanford, student participation in administration, student housing, and tuition costs. Materials range in date from 1968 to 2017 (bulk 1968-1976 and 2013-2017).
Related Material
Black Graduate and Professional Student Association Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
The GPSC handbook [serial].
Medical Center Library.
Records and Papers of Terry Sanford, 1945-1998
University Archives, Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains electronic records. Access copies of electronic records must be accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records of the Executive Committee are restricted for ten years from the origin of the material.
Graduate students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Postsecondary education -- United States -- Costs; Student protest; Student participation in administration; Duke University -- Student housing; Duke University -- Graduate students; Sanford, Terry; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; Duke University. Graduate and Professional Student Council; Duke University. Graduate School
- An Orientation to the Graduate and Professional Student Council, by Barrett Koster, 1987 (Box 1)
- Annual Reports, 1968-1975 (Box 1)
- Committee Memberships, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
- Committee Reports, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- Committee Review Board, 1976 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, ASDU, 1972 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, John O. Blackburn, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Terry Sanford, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
- Chartering Policy, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
- Clerical aide and office space, ca. 1972-1973 (Box 1)
- Constitution, 1968 (Box 2)
- Creation of GSA (includes information on the vigil and Allen Building Takeover), 1968-1969 (Box 2)
- Deferred tuition plan, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
- Department representatives, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
- Early history of the GSA, ca. 1973 (Box 2)
- Environmental Center Search Committee, 1973 (Box 2)
- Financial records, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
- Foreign language questionnaire, 1968 (Box 2)
- Graduate Center (proposed), 1975 (Box 2)
- Graduate Life Committee, 1972 (Box 2)
- Graduate School, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
- Graduate School, organizational structure, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
- Member directory, 1971-1976 (Box 2)
- Graduate Student Association President's notes, 1969-1974 (Box 2)
- Graduate student guidebook, correspondence and related materials, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
- Graduate student housing, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
- Graduate student questionnaires, ca. 1970-1971 (Box 2)
- Graduate student questionnaires, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
- Judicial Procedures, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
- Judicial Procedures, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
- Judicial Procedures, Graduate Student Association statements, undated (Box 3)
- Legal Insurance, 1977 (Box 3)
- Letters to students, 1969-1974 (Box 3)
- Library meeting, grievances presented by the Graduate Student Association, 1971 (Box 3)
- Library hours petition, 1972 (Box 3)
- Membership roster, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
- Membership roster, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
- Membership roster, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
- Membership roster, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
- Minutes, 1968-1976 (Box 3)
- Newsletter, 1972-1973, undated (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1968-2000 (Box 3)
- NC-PIRG, 1971 (Box 4)
- Procedures and Function of Officers, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
- Referenda (that Duke University to sustain the Graduate Student Association), 1970-1973 (Box 4)
- Residential Life Committee, 1970-1975 (Box 4)
- Traffic Commission, 1972 (Box 4)
- University Committees, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
- University Planning Commission, undated (Box 4)
- University Regulations, 1968-1971 (Box 4)
- University Union, 1971 (Box 4)
- X-Rated Film Policy, 1977 (Box 4)
- Yeager, William-Personal Notes as President of GSA, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
- Flyers, undated (Box 4)
- Graduate Student Guidebook, 1971-1975, 1977-1978, 1994 (Box 4)
- Graduate Student Association newsletter, 1968-1974 (Box 4)
- Executive Committee meeting minutes, 2013-2016; 40 files; approximately 10 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0001)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Executive Committee records restricted until 2026.
  Scope and Contents
  Document files in PDF and MS Word formats.
- Executive Committee documents and meeting materials, 2014-2015; 27 files; approximately 20 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0001)
  Executive Committee records restricted until 2025.
  Document files in PDF, MS Word, MS Excel, and MS Powerpoint formats.
- Executive Committee agendas, 2015; 6 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0001)
  Document files in PDF format.
- Executive Committee email messages, 2012-2015; 2273 files; approximately 300 megabytes (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0001)
  Email message files in MIME Email and MBOX formats.
- GPSC budgets, 2011-2015 and undated; 10 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0001)
  Document files in MS Excel, MS Word, and PDF formats.
- GPSC house event notes, 2014; 1 file; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0001)
  Executive Committee records restricted until 2024.
  Document file in PDF format.
- President records, 2015-2016; 28 files; approximately 30 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0001)
  Document files in MS Word, MS Excel, MS PowerPoint, and PDF formats, as well as an image file in JPEG format.
- GPSC bylaws, 2014-2015; 2 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0002)
- Affilliated student groups, 2016-2017; 90 files; approximately 20 megabytes (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0002)
  Document files in MS Word, PDF, MS Excel, and plain text formats.
- Archives from 2010-2015 website, 2017; 5 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0002)
- Committee work, 2016-2017; 8 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0002)
  Document files in MS Excel format.
- Event photos, 2013-2015 (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0002)
  Image files in JPEG format.
- General Assembly records, 2013-2016; 74 files; approximately 80 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0002)
  Document files in PDF, MS Word, MS PowerPoint, and MS Excel formats.
- GPSC Logo files, 2014; 6 files; approximately 5 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA31-10-0001-SET-0002)
  Image files in JPEG format and graphic design files in EPS format.